- I wake up in the morning
and I want to reach for my phone,
but I know that even
if I were to crank up the brightness
on that phone screen,
it's not bright enough
to trigger that cortisol spike,
and for me to be at my most alert
and focused throughout the day
and to optimize my sleep at night.
So what I do is I get out of bed
and I go outside,
and if it's a bright, clear day,
and the sun is low in the sky,
or the sun is starting to get overhead,
what we call low solar angle,
then I know I'm getting
outside at the right time.
If there's cloud cover
and I can't see the sun,
I also know I'm doing a good thing
because it turns out
especially on cloudy days,
you want to get outside
and get as much light energy
or photons in your eyes.
But let's say it's a very clear day
and I can see where the sun is,
I do not need to stare
directly into the sun.
If it's very low in the sky,
I might do that
because it's not going to be
very painful to my eyes.
However, if the sun is
a little bit brighter
and a little bit higher in the sky,
sometimes it could be painful to look at.
So the way to get this sunlight viewing
early in the day
is to look toward the sun.
If it's too bright to look at directly,
well then don't do that.
You just look toward it,
but not directly at it.
It's absolutely fine to blink.
In fact, I encourage you to blink
whenever you feel the impulse to blink.
Never look at any light,
sunlight or otherwise
that's so bright that
it's painful to look at
'cause you can damage your eyes.
But for this morning sunlight viewing,
it's best to not wear sunglasses.
That's right, to not wear sunglasses
at least for this
morning sunlight viewing.
It is absolutely fine
to wear eyeglasses or contact lenses,
so-called corrective lenses.
In fact, those will serve you well
in this practice or this tool
because they will focus the light
onto your neural retina and onto those
melanopsin intrinsically
photosensitive ganglion cells.
If your eyeglasses or contact lenses
have UV protection, that's okay.
There's so many different
wavelengths of light
coming from the sun
and they are bright enough
that they will trigger the mechanisms
that you want triggered
at this early time of day.
So try and get outside,
ideally within the first five minutes
of waking or maybe it's 15 minutes,
but certainly within the
first hour after waking.
I want to share with you
three critical things
about this tool of
morning sunlight viewing.
First of all, this is not
some woo biology thing.
This is grounded in the
core of our physiology.
There are literally hundreds,
if not thousands of quality
peer reviewed papers
showing that light
viewing early in the day
is the most powerful stimulus
for wakefulness throughout the day
and it has a powerful, positive impact
on your ability to fall
and stay asleep at night.
So this is really the
foundational power tool
for ensuring a great night's sleep
and for feeling more awake during the day.
Second of all, if you wake up
before the sun is out,
you can and probably should
flip on artificial lights
in your internal home environment
or apartment or wherever
you happen to live,
if your goal is to be awake, right?
If you wake up at four
in the morning and you need to be awake,
well then turn on artificial lights.
Once the sun is out however,
once the sun has risen,
then you still want to get
outside and view sunlight.
Some of you will wake up
before the sun comes out.
And if you're asking whether or not
turning on artificial lights
can replace sunlight at those hours,
unfortunately the answer is no.
Unless you have a very special light,
we'll talk about what kind of light,
the bright artificial lights
in your home environment are not,
I repeat, are not going
to be sufficiently bright
to turn on the cortisol mechanism
and the other wake up mechanisms
that you need early in the day.
The diabolical twist however
is that those lights in
your home or apartment,
or even on your phone
are bright enough to disrupt your sleep
if you look at them too late at night
or in the middle of the night.
So there's this asymmetry in our retinal,
our eye biology and in our brain's biology
whereby early in the day,
right around waking,
you need a lot of light,
a lot of photons,
a lot of light energy
and artificial lights
generally just won't accomplish
what you need them to accomplish.
But at night, even a little bit
of artificial light can really mess up
your so-called circadian,
your 24-hour clocks
and all these mechanisms
that we're talking about.
So if you wake up before the sun is out
and it's still dark,
please turn on as many
bright artificial lights
as you possibly can or need,
but then get outside
once the sun is out.
On cloudy days, you especially
need to get outside.
I repeat, on cloudy days, overcast days,
you especially need to get
outside and get sunlight.
You just need to get more of it.
Now, how much light
and how much light viewing do you need?
This is going to vary depending
on person and place,
literally where you live on earth,
whether or not there's
a lot of tree cover,
whether or not you're somebody
who has sensitive eyes
or less sensitive eyes.
It's really impossible for me to give
an absolute prescriptive,
but we can give some general guidelines.
In general, on a clear day,
meaning no cloud cover
or minimal cloud cover,
you want to get this sunlight exposure
to your eyes for about five minutes or so,
could be three minutes one day,
it could be seven minutes the next day,
about five minutes.
On a day where there's cloud cover,
so the sun is just
peeking through the clouds
or it's more dense cloud cover,
you want to get about 10 minutes
of sunlight exposure to
your eyes early in the day.
And on days that are
really densely overcast
or maybe even are rainy,
you're going to want to get as much
as 20 or 30 minutes of sunlight exposure.
Another key thing is,
do not forget about just don't try
and get this sunlight exposure
through a windshield of a car or a window,
whether or not it's tinted or otherwise.
It takes far too long.
It's simply not going to trigger
the relevant mechanisms,
you would be standing there all day
trying to get enough light
into your eyes from the morning sunlight.
And by then, the sun
will have already moved
from low solar angle to overhead
and it simply won't work for all sorts
of mechanisms related to
your circadian rhythm functions.
So just don't try and do it
through a windshield,
sunglasses or a window.
It's just not going to work.
Get outside.
If the weather is really bad
or for whatever reason, safety reasons,
you cannot get outside,
well then I suppose, try
and get near a window.
That would be the last, last resort,
but you really want to get outside
to get the sunlight exposure.
[upbeat music]